Hey, welcome to the centerfuge where I
take health podcasts and other shows and
essentially fact check them by bringing
forward the studies behind the claims.
Are they accurate or are they not? In
this episode, we'll be getting into
breakfast specifically. So, the topics
are sugar and glucose spikes. Is it so
simple?
Could how you eat your food impact the
glucose spikes that you experience? And
I know this may seem blasphemous, but
are glucose spikes even a concern in the
first place? Now, I'm mentioning glucose
spikes for good reason. Because in
today's episode, continuing the J Shetty
podcast guest breakdown. We're going
over what Jesse Ashuspi, hopefully
that's somewhat correct, has to say, but
she's better known as the glucose
goddess. Now, bow you peasant.
No, no, I I wasn't serious. You didn't
actually need to bow. The goddess is a
French biochemist and New York Times
bestseller according to her website. As
usual, I'll supply summaries at the end,
but let's get into it.
>> The glucose spikes that we experience
after breakfast is going to control the
rest of our day. So, if you eat in the
morning something that is pure glucose,
like most of us do, right? I grew up on
orange juice and Nutella crepes, so I
know
>> sounds amazing. [laughter]
It was amazing. But then at 10:30, I was
exhausted because I was crashing. My
glucose levels were crashing and I was
super super hungry because after a big
spike, you experience a big crash. And
that crash activates the craving center
in your brain and literally tells you,
Jay, go find some chocolate, you know,
and you cannot resist
>> what that voice sounds like. [laughter]
>> And you can't resist that urge. So, your
breakfast, if you're having a big
glucose spike at breakfast, you're
setting yourself up for a day of
cravings, fatigue, inflammation, and
you're going to feel quite awful.
>> Okay, a lot packed in there. First, if
you eat a sweet breakfast, you'll
experience a glucose spike, which will
lead to a crash later on, controlling
the rest of your day. Now, believe it or
not, this is complex to break down
because there's a lot of variables when
considering breakfast as a whole, but
I'll do my best here. Madmoiselle
Goddess is absolutely right that sugar
generally increases our postmeal blood
glucose levels termed a glucose spike.
This is evidenced in studies like this
one where participants were given the
same breakfast mostly carbohydrates and
then paired that breakfast with one of
several drinks. So two with a load of
glucose and fructose like regular table
sugar and others with other forms of
sugar. So milk associated sugar like
lactose. Now we don't need to worry
about those details. Just look at the
graph of their blood glucose levels
after eating and drinking these
different breakfasts. They all led to a
glucose spike around that 45minute mark
with sugarsw sweetened coffee leading to
the greatest spike. Speaking to Jesse's
point, however, I'll also have you note
that they tested orange juice at exactly
the same amount of sugar and they did
not experience a greater glucose spike
compared to even water. So, this speaks
to other variables also playing a role
outside of just sugar. Plus also notice
that the return of the blood glucose to
normal levels happened at a similar
speed across the conditions. So it seems
that carbohydrateheavy and even
sugarheavy breakfasts don't lead to a
crash. But there's two more points to be
said in defense of Jesse's point. One,
this study compared against other
carbohydrates. So maybe we'd detect an
effect when comparing against other
foods. We'll be getting into more depth
on that point soon. Two, there is
wellestablished evidence across decades
of work that different foods have
different effects on our blood sugar.
This is called the glycemic index. So
that means that certain foods are
generally going to lead to faster
entrance of glucose molecules from sugar
into the bloodstream leading to a
glucose spike. That means that if you
eat a food in isolation, you will
absolutely experience a glucose spike
greater than another food. and some of
those foods like rice, breads, uh
breakfast cereals, and simpler
carbohydrates. The issue here, as we saw
in the first study, is that we don't eat
foods in isolation typically for
breakfast. And the matrix of the food
that hits your stomach makes a huge
impact on if we get a glucose spike or
not. So the takeaway at this point is
yes, many foods in isolation cause
glucose spikes, but the matrix of the
food can reduce or increase that glucose
spike. And simply looking at the sugar
content is really insufficient to
predict a glucose spike. We'll get more
into that soon. We'll listen some more.
Now,
>> an important switch to make is to switch
from a sweet breakfast to a savory
breakfast built around protein. Right?
Whatever kind of protein you like. Maybe
it's dairy, maybe it's tofu, maybe it's
protein powder, maybe it's leftover fish
from last night, maybe it's eggs,
whatever kind of protein you want,
that's going to keep your glucose levels
nice and steady.
>> So, is the secret to reducing glucose
spikes protein? Generally, yes. We see
that across many studies like this one,
where participants had their blood
glucose measured similarly to what we
previously went over. And you can see
that two of the lines are dramatically
blunted compared to the others. These
two conditions specifically contained
more protein. But that also came at the
expense of fats and importantly
carbohydrates. So was it the protein or
the reduction in the blood glucose
stimulating nutrient, the carbohydrates?
Unfortunately, we can't say based off
these data, but there's a consistent
theme across other studies that
including protein reduces glucose
spikes. And when looking at other
studies that maintain the same amount of
carbohydrates and only raise protein in
a step-wise fashion, there's a reduction
in blood glucose. More whey protein,
less glucose in the blood within the
measurement period. Okay, so excellent.
Jesse is spot on. Okay, so what we know
so far is that different sugar sources
cause different blood glucose spikes.
They aren't all equal, but if we want to
guarantee a reduced blood glucose spike,
then add protein to the meal. Next,
Jesse is going to go over a hack on how
to eat your breakfast and the impact
that it has on well glucose spikes. Now,
in addition, I'd like to go over if we
should even be worried about these
glucose spikes because I think that
context is really important. Add some
healthy fats in there and you can have
some starch like a slice of bread for
taste. But importantly, a savory
breakfast contains nothing sweet except
if you want some for taste, some whole
fruit, right? And you know all those
sweet breakfast foods that you love, you
don't have to say goodbye to them
completely. The best time to have them
is for dessert after lunch or after
dinner. Because if you eat something
that contains a lot of glucose,
something starchy or sweet after a meal,
>> the glucose molecules are not going to
arrive as quickly into your bloodstream
because there's already going to be food
in your stomach.
>> The worst time to eat starches and
sugars is breakfast
>> because your body is super empty. So,
anything you eat goes to your
bloodstream in a second, right? But it's
actually the meal of the day where most
of us
>> eat just starches and sugars. Yeah.
>> Think about the typical breakfast.
Orange juice, oats with honey on them,
breakfast cereal, you know, fruit
smoothies,
>> oatmeal with raisins.
>> Exactly. And then you wonder why most of
us feel so terrible throughout the day.
Why it's 400 p.m. and we're exhausted
and we need coffee or Red Bull. We have
cravings all throughout the day and even
at night. Your breakfast controls how
you feel for the whole day.
>> So, the goddess herself is talking about
switching to a savory breakfast.
generally things that are lower
carbohydrate like eggs, avocado, and so
on. In fact, just such a study exists
comparing a carbohydrate- richch
breakfast containing a bagel to eggs.
Now, both breakfasts were calorically
the same, and we can see that the
carbohydrate dominant breakfast led to
greater glucose spikes. Now, it doesn't
look like much, but that's because we're
looking at mill per liter instead of
milligram per deciliter. And in fact,
hunger also rebounded more quickly, too.
To Jesse's point about cravings, as the
higher the lines go, the greater the
people's hunger. To be fair, the
difference wasn't huge, but it's still
present, and we don't know how much that
it might have widened if the experiment
had lasted longer. On top of that, she
briefly mentions that food order may
matter. For example, consuming anything
sweet after savory as opposed to before.
There is data to back that up, too, like
this study that she enjoys referencing
in other content. In fact, I did a deep
dive on this very concept in another
video and there are some limitations
though the overall idea is correct. Now,
the takeaway these last few points
mentioned is that yes, focusing on
savory breakfast as well as putting any
sweet foods that you consume last in the
order of eating reduces your blood
glucose spike. The glucose goddess is
goddessing. Still, something doesn't sit
well with me about all this. And it's
not indigestion or a glucose spike. It's
the question of should we even be
worried about any of this. I'm going to
touch on that next as I've done deep
dives on that very question before,
including multiple studies. Before I
touch on it again for you here, I have a
more extensive version of this video
that you're watching, which includes
more on how to time protein, how to
think about protein in your meals, and
the strange effects that mixed meals
have on your blood sugar, your blood
glucose. Now, if you're interested,
check out my Physionic Insiders
platform. It grants you access to what I
just went over in video and written
form, but also comes with a ton of other
searchable material and all these perks
right over here. Plus, you keep this
kind of work alive. So, consider joining
the insiders. The link to check it all
out is in the description box. Okay,
glucose spikes. Are they even a problem?
Well, the glucose goddess brand is based
largely, if not entirely, on this one
problem. But honestly, the evidence in
the literature is a lot less certain.
When I looked over the studies, it
seemed to me that we are misinterpreting
or misrepresenting the studies. While on
social media, we focus on the top of the
spike, the research focuses on the point
2 hours after the meal consumption.
Meaning that if a person's blood glucose
is below 140 milligs per deciliter, so
that's 7.8 mill per liter, that's a
normal reading. So of course if we use
the same numbers but we move them up to
the 45minute mark almost everyone's
blood glucose will be much greater. Is
that a reason for panic? Highly likely
not simply because that's not how the
measurements are supposed to be
interpreted. So the blood glucose spikes
can and often do extend beyond the 140
mg per deciliters but the true measure
is 2 hours later not the peak of the
spike itself. In addition I pointed this
out in a graph in my previous analysis
which indicates that the amount of time
of day that we spend in different ranges
of blood glucose if we're healthy.
Granted, it's a small sample of people,
but even so, look at the amount of time
above 140. What is that? Like a few
percent. That translates to less than an
hour total. Is that really meaningful if
your blood glucose is well below that
the overwhelming majority of the day? I
have my strong doubts, but I'd certainly
be open to other research indicating
otherwise. Still, many people have
glucose spikes that last longer than 2
hour the 2-hour threshold. And for those
people, it's possible that glucose
spikes are a problem. I would still
focus on the underlying issues like
overall insulin resistance rather than
glucose spikes themselves. But I'd be
more concerned if a if people are
pre-diabetic or diabetic. Okay, as
usual, that was a lot. So, how do we
package this up nicely? Well, I think
that we're overindexing on the harm of
sweet foods without contextualizing
things correctly. One, we know that
carbohydrate foods tend to raise blood
glucose or blood sugar more. However,
even within carbohydrateheavy foods,
there's a lot of difference even within
equal sugar consumption. Two, you can
reduce your blood glucose spikes by
simply mixing your carbohydrates and
sweet foods with protein. Three, you can
also reduce your blood glucose spikes by
changing the order of your food,
consuming your carbohydrate or sweet
foods after your savory. And four,
I'm not convinced that glucose spikes
are a concern for people who are
generally healthy. They may be more of
an issue for diabetic and pre-diabetic
individuals, but if you have a glucose
monitor and your blood glucose returns
to less than 140 milligrams per
deciliter, remember that's about like a
7.8 8 mill moles per liter within 2
hours of eating your food, you're
probably fine. If it stays above that
for much longer, then it may be worth
using uh some of the tricks that we
outlined here. But the best bang for
your buck would be to focus on improving
your overall insulin sensitivity.
Finally, I'll also add that people can
feel off due to glucose spikes, which
comes down to personal preference. In
such a case, you can still use the
points that were brought up. At any
rate, hopefully you feel a bit more
certain on the topic. If you want more
health separation of what's
scientifically accurate and what's not,
then check out the next episode of the
centerfuge right here. Otherwise, I do
deeper analysis on Jesse's points on
meal timing right here. And I'll add
links to my other work on the topic in
the description. I hope this helped.
Catch you in the next one. See you.